Preliminary Guide to the Paul B. Beeson Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Paul B. Beeson papers
1940-2001
1982-2001
MS 1789
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.25
(2 boxes)
The papers include correspondence, lectures and writings, and photographs that date primarily from Paul Beeson's later years. They include honors and tributes from former students and colleagues and attest to the influence Beeson had as a teacher.
Beeson, Paul B. (Paul Bruce), 1908-2006
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Paul B. Beeson, 2001; Richard Rapport, 2010.
Biographical / Historical
Paul Bruce Beeson was born in 1908 in Livingston, Montana, but grew up in Anchorage, Alaska. He attended the University of Washington and after graduating from McGill Medical School in 1933, he completed an internship at the University of Pennsylvania Hospital. He then joined his father in general practice in Ohio. In 1939, he became chief resident at the Peter Bent Brigham Hospital and in 1942 joined the Emory University medical faculty. In 1946 he became chairman of the Department of Medicine there. From 1952 until 1965, Beeson served as chairman of the Department of Medicine at Yale University, leaving to become the Nuffield Professor of Clinical Medicine at Oxford University. In 1974, he returned to the United States to accept appointment as the Distinguished Physician of the U.S. Veterans Administration in Seattle, Washington. Beeson died on August 14, 2006, in Exeter, New Hampshire.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The papers include correspondence, lectures and writings, and photographs that date primarily from Paul Beeson's later years. They include honors and tributes from former students and colleagues and attest to the influence Beeson had as a teacher.
Internal medicine -- Study and teaching; Medicine -- Practice; Beeson, Paul B. (Paul Bruce), 1908-2006; Yale University. School of Medicine
- Original Accession, 1940-2000
  - Association of American Physicians, 1984-1996 (Box 1)
  - Canadian Society of Internal Medicine, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Cecil Textbook of Medicine, 1959, 1982-1995 (Box 1)
  - Certificates, 1945-1991 (Box 1)
  - Commonwealth Fund, 1984-1993 (Box 1)
  - Harvard Unit, 1940-1942, 1990-1993 (Box 1)
  - Interplanetary Society [Pus Club], 1997 (Box 1)
  - Lectures given, 1979-1995 (Box 1)
  - Lee, Richard V. [interview with Beeson for Annals of Internal Medicine ], 1998-2000 (Box 1)
  - Licenses, 1948-1994 (Box 1)
  - Markey Trust, 1986 (Box 1)
  - McDermott, Walsh, 1957, 1981-1983 (Box 1)
  - National Academies, 1998-2000 (Box 1)
  - National Institutes of Health, 1984-1987 (Box 1)
  - New York Academy of Medicine, 1999-2001 (Box 1)
  - Norham Gardens, 13 [Osler's house], 1987-1995 (Box 1)
  - Oxford Textbook of Geriatric Medicine, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Oxford Textbook of Medicine, 1982-1984 (Box 1)
  - Paul Beeson Physician Faculty Scholars in Aging Research Program, 1994-2000 (Box 1)
  - Pharos, 1982
  - Photographs, 1942-1992 (Box 1)
  - Physicians for Human Rights, 1987-1991 (Box 1)
  - Physicians for Social Responsibility, 1983-2000 (Box 1)
  - Royal College of Physicians, 1977-1995 (Box 1)
  - Royal Society of Medicine, 1975-1992 (Box 1)
  - Stead Research Scholarship Fund, 1985-1986 (Box 1)
  - University of Alabama at Birmingham, 1987, 1997, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Wood, William Barry, 1971, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Yale-New Haven Hospital. Beeson Medical Service [includes photographs], 1996 (Box 1)
  - Yale University. Beeson Colloquium and Fitkin Iron Terns Reunion, 1993-1997 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, 1969-1996; Accession 2010-M-091
  - Biographical information and curriculum vitae of Paul Beeson, 1969-1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence of Paul Beeson with Richard Rapport, 1980-1996 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)